Minnesota Geological Survey Field Notebooks, 1877-1990
University of Minnesota Libraries
Minnesota Geological Survey field notebooks
1877-1990
University of Minnesota Libraries. University of Minnesota Archives [uarc]
Geological Survey of Minnesota
31 boxes (15.5 cubic feet)
This collection contains field notebooks complete by personnel of the Minnesota Geological Survey, and its predecessor, the Minnesota Geological and Natural History Survey.
uarc 895
Administrative Information
Use of Materials
Items in this collection do not circulate and may be used in-house only.
Source of acquisition
Notebooks housed in the first three boxes of the collection were deposited in the University of Minnesota Archives by the Geology Department; the remaining notebooks were deposited by the Minnesota Geological Survey in July 2007.
Arrangement
Many of the notebooks were assigned an arbitrary number by the Minnesota Geological Survey for filing and tracking purposes. Not all notebooks were numbered and many numbers were not used. For ease of use, field notebooks are arranged alphabetically by “author.” For reference purposes, the numerical list maintained by MGS is in Box 4, folder 1.
Removed from the collection were several notebooks by Alexander Winchell (brother of Newton H. Winchell) and his colleagues at the Michigan Geological Survey. However, Winchell’s field notes on work done in Minnesota for MGNHS were retained. Several other notebooks which seemed of little value as they were undated and unrecorded were put aside for disposal.
Separate collections were created for sets of field notes maintained by Christopher Hall (collection 731) and Newton Horace Winchell (collection 981). They include both private work, work done for the U.S. Geological Survey as well as work done for MGNHS.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of field notebooks created by the personnel of Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS), and its predecessor, the Minnesota Geological and Natural History Survey (MGNHS). The field notebooks contain basic data used in many of the survey’s annual reports and bulletins.
Of special note are the field notes kept by Ulysses S. Grant who did most of his work in Northern Minnesota on the North Shore. His notes are among the most complete and include a study of the gold mining along Rainy Lake (Box 1, folders 6-7; Box 2, folders 8-9). Others, while more sketchy, contain a great deal of information about Minnesota geology and natural history.
Some of the volumes are in poor condition, with broken bindings and loose pages.
Historical Note
The Minnesota Geological and Natural History Survey (MGNHS) was established on 1 March 1872 by an act of the legislature and the University of Minnesota was placed in charge of conducting the survey. Newton H. Winchell was brought to the University in 1872 to direct the survey. Winchell resigned in 1900 causing the survey to be abandoned until 1911 when William H. Emmons was hired to be the new head of the Geology department and director of the survey, renamed the Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS).
Related Materials in University Archives
William Watts Folwell papers
Christopher Webber Hall papers
Newton Horace Winchell papers
Minnesota Geological and Natural History Survey records
Minnesota Geological Survey records
Bell Museum of Natural History records
Board of Regents records
Comptroller records
Department of Botany records
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the University of Minnesota Libraries. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Broderick, T. M. (Thomas Monteith), b. 1889.; Grant, Ulysses Sherman, 1867-1932.; Grout, Frank F. (Frank Fitch), b. 1880.; Morey, G. B.; Schwartz, George M. (George Melvin), 1892-; Upham, Warren, 1850-1934.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.; Geological and Natural History Survey of Minnesota.; Geological Survey of Minnesota.; Botany--Minnesota.; Geology--Minnesota.
Detailed Contents of Collection
The following section contains a detailed list of the materials in the collection.
- Author unknown
  - Vermilion District, 1990. (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Wisconsin Geological Survey, undated. (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - New Brighton profile, undated. (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Houston County, undated. (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Redwood County, undated. (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Brown County, undated. (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Vermiculite research, 1944. (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Duluth - Outcrop sample notes, 1978-1979. (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Washington County Sheets, undated. (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Gunflint Lake, Canada, 1961. (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Field notes, 1968-1969. (Box 30)
- Adams, E. Maurice: Vermilion, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Adams, Robert: Notes on Cuyuna, circa 1944-1953. (Box 21, Folder 10)
- Allen, Victor T.: North St. Louis County, 1921. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Allison, Ira S.: Giants Range, 1923-1924.; 2 volumes (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Alt, David: Burntside area, 1956.; 5 volumes (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
- Alvarado, Ben: Anorthosite problem, 1936. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Anderson, Daniel H.
  - Saganaga Lake/Northern Light Lake, 1961. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Rove Recon and survey, South Lake, quad V, 1962. (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Austin, George S.: Clay deposits, Goodhue County, 1962.; 2 volumes (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Austin, George S. and Barton D. Gross: Magnetics - McLeod, 1962.; 6 volumes (Box 22, Folder 8-10)
- Ayers, Horace Beemer
  - Carleton County: Forests, water power, fires, 1893-1984. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carleton County: Barometric readings, 1894. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baker, Bob: Baker and students, 1988.; 2 volumes (Box 24, Folder 10)
- Balk, Robert R.: Snowbank structures, 1930. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Bell, W. Charles: Field notes, 1949. (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Berg, G.A.: Minnesota Valley, Thesis, undated. (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Bergquist, Harlan R.
  - Stratigraphy, No. 25, 1936. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Book No. 23-24, 26, 1934, 1937.; 3 volumes (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
- Bergquist, Harlan R. and Clinton R. Stauffer
  - Stratigraphy, 1934. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Stratigraphy, No. 21, 1934. (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Berkey, Charles Peter: St. Louis County, 1893. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains topography and barometer readings.
- Bickford, K.F.: Clay samples, 1947.; 2 volumes (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Bowles, Oliver: Field notes on investigation of Minnesota quarries, undated, 1894-1903.; 2 volumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bradley, Edward: Twin City water problem, 1949. (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Broderick, Thomas M.
  - T 63-4, R 8-9, Lake County, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - T63-4-5, R 4-5-6 W., 1915. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cook County, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Reproduction.
  - T 64, R 3, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Little Saganaga, 1916.; 2 volumes (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Poplar Lake, 1916.; 3 volumes (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Gabemichigama to Tuscarora, undated. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - East Mesabi, 1917.; 3 volumes (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Gunflint, 1919. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Brown, Ronald: Rove Slate Area, 1925. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Brownell, George: Western Ontario, Canada, 1926. (Box 23, Folder 8)
- Cowin, Percy G.
  - Peat reports, 1915.; 2 volumes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Plant samples, 1915. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    See also Edgar K. Soper who was working with Cowin for part of 1915.
- Cram, Ira and John W. Gruner: Rainy Lake-Burntside Lake, 1923. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Culver, Garry Eugene: Topographic and barometric records in Northern Minnesota, 1893.; 2 volumes (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dalrymple, James: Vermilion, 1951-1952.; 5 volumes (Box 15, Folder 2-4)
- Davidson, Don M.: Rove Slate Area, 1925.; 3 volumes (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
- Davis, C.A.: Notes on Minnesota peat, 1913-1914. (Box 23, Folder 7)
- Dolence, Jerry D.: Notes on Pokegama quartzite, 1959. (Box 23, Folder 9)
- Duerr, Robert: Cuyuna, 1905-1906.; 2 volumes (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Dutton, Carl E.
  - Knife Lake slate problem, undated.; 2 volumes (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Volumes noted as Book 1 and Book 3.
  - Ensign Lake, undated. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Volume noted as Book 2.
- Edwards, M.G.
  - T 63-5 N, R 3-8 W, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - T 64 N, R 1-4 W, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - T 61-3 N, R 4 W, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Elftman, Arthur Hugo
  - Topography and barometrical, 1893.; 2 volumes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Specimens and rocks, 1895-1887. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Erdmann, Charles E.: Compassman, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Gibson, George R.
  - Knife Lake slate, 1931-1933.; 8 volumes (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
  - Heavy residues, Pokegamo, 1934. (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Gilmer, Todd: Rochester metro area, 1964-1966. (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Grant, Ulysses Sherman
  - Natural history of the Lake Vermilion area, 1886. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Canadian border, 1888-1892.; 2 volumes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Canadian border, 1892-1893 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - North Shore, circa 1893-1899. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mapping report of gold near Rainy Lake, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gray, Anton: Rove Slate Area, 1925. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Griffin, William L.
  - Embarrass-Babbitt area, 1964.; 3 volumes (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Book 6, 1966. (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Grout, Frank F.
  - North Shore work - Grand Marais, 1914. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - T 61-3, R 9-11, E. of East Mesaba, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - T 63-4, R7-8-9, West Lake County Mesaba, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - T-63 N, R 3, West Lake County Mesaba, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - T 63 N, R 4 W, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - East Greenwood-Crocodile-McFarland Road, 1915. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gabbro; General North Shore area, 1916. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Intensities - Remarks, 1916. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes remarks from Thomas M. Broderick.
  - St. Louis County, 1922. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gabemichigama east to Gunflint, 1935. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - East Mesabi, 1917.; 3 volumes (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Old Mesabi, undated. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Crane Lake, undated. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Myrtle Lake, 1919. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Vermilion, 1920.; 3 volumes (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Turtle Lake, 1920. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Burntside, Coutchiching, Ash River, 1921. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - St. Louis County, 1921.; 2 volumes (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - North St. Louis County, 1921. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Lake and Cook Counties, 1922, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - High Lake, 1924. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Seine River, Highway No. 1 Basswood Lake, 1924. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Saganaga, Ogishke, 1925. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rove Slate Area, 1925-1928.; 6 volumes (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
  - Lake of the Woods, 1927. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rainy Lake, 1927. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Saganaga, 1928, 1932. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Inclusions in Gabbro, 1928. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Snowbank structure, 1930. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Saganaga structure, 1931. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Saganaga structure, 1931, 1933, 1936. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - South Part Gabbro - Lake County, 1935. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Knife Lake slate structure, 1932.; 2 volumes (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Anorthosites, 1931, 1934, 1936.; 5 volumes (Box 13, Folder 7-9)
  - Wanless area, 1937. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Duluth Book F, undated. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Duluth Book G (Magnetics), 1914. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sampling TiO2 and mapping Cook County, 1936-1937. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Brule Lake, 1938-1939.; 2 volumes (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - T 63 N, R 2 W, 1939. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Cook County, 1938-1939.; 2 volumes (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
  - Clay studies, 1942-1943. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Central Minnesota, 1945. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Goudreau (Ontario), Giant's Range, Morton, 1942. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Cook County - Above Highway 61, 1939. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Cook County - Near Good Harbor Bay, 1939-1940. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Also includes notes by Richard C. Marmaduke.
  - Cook County, 1940.; 3 volumes (Box 20, Folder 5, 8)
  - T 61 N, R 5 W, 1940. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Cook County, 1954-1956. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Cook County, 1941. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Cook County, 1946. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Cook County - near Shore and Hovland, 1946. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Cook County, 1947.; 3 volumes (Box 21, Folder 4-6)
  - R 3 and 4 E, 1946. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Cook County and drilling Tucker Lake, 1947. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Gunflint, 1942. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Ti Magnetite drill, 1943. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Cuyuna, T46-29,30, 1941-1948. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Cuyuna, T47-29, 1941-1951. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Cuyuna Notes, 1941-1942. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Cuyuna Mesabi iron, 1945-1946. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Late notes on Cuyuna, 1953-1954. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Keweenawan, E-C Minnesota, 1908-1909.; 2 volumes (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Collecting samples for heavy accessories Giants Range, 1935. (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Alworth Hole, Mesabi, 1944. (Box 25, Folder 6)
    Book attributed to Frank Grout.
  - Original field notes for Bull 28, 1947. (Box 25, Folder 7)
- Gruner, John W.
  - Gunflint, 1919. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Mesabi Range, 1922. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Vermilion, undated. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 13-23 W., 1923. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Burntside Lake T63NR13W, 1923. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mesabi, 1942-1945. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rove Slate Area, 1926.; 2 volumes (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Volume 2 includes additional notes by George M. Schwartz, dated 1927.
  - Knife Lake Slate problem, 1928-1933.; 16 volumes (Box 12, Folder 3-10)
  - Knife Lake Slate problem, 1931-1932.; 4 volumes (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Vermilion detail - Knife Lake problem, 1932-1933, 1936.; 3 volumes (Box 14, Folder 9-10)
  - Knife Lake slate problem, 1934.; 2 volumes (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Knife Lake slate problem, 1923.; 2 volumes (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Horn, 1925.; 3 volumes (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
  - Lake of the Woods County, 1936. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Michigan and Wisconsin, 1936. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Knife Lake slate problem, 1939. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Gold prospects, 1925. (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Gryc, George: Cook County, Grand Portage area, 1941.; 3 volumes (Box 20, Folder 9-10)
- Hanley, Franklin B.
  - Vermilion, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Vermilion and Turtle, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Turtle Lake, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - St. Louis County, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Glacial geology of Northeastern Minnesota, undated. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Hanson, Gilbert N.
  - Snowbank Lake area, 1961. (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Traverse from South Kawishiwi River to Ely, 1960. (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Harder, Edmund C.: Gunflint, 1906-1907. (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Harrington, M. W.: Botany of Olmstead and Dodge counties, 1875. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Harris, J. Merle
  - State parks, 1950-1951.; 3 volumes (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - Uranium survey, 1949.; 2 volumes (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Geiger records, 1949. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Cu-Ni Duluth Gabbro, 1952-1953.; 3 volumes (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
- Hogberg, Rudolph K.
  - St. Cloud Sheet, 1964. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Industrial minerals, 1963-1966.; 3 volumes (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
  - RMA, 1971-1972.; 3 volumes (Box 27, Folder 5-6)
- Johnston, Stanwood
  - Crane Lake (Traverse notes), 1919. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Vermilion, 1920.; 3 volumes (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Turtle Lake, 1920. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Jones, Norris W.
  - Forest center and Ensign Lake quads, 1962.; 2 volumes (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Forest center and Ensign Lake quads, 1962. (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Hovland area, 1960.; 3 volumes (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
  - South Lake quadrangle, 1963, 1966.; 2 volumes (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Field maps and air photos used in preparing MGS RI 29, 1961. (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Juni, Benjamin: North Shore, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  List of Carex identified at the University; many of the plants were specimens collected on the North Shore.
- Kiehle, F.A.: North Shore, Lake Superior, 1891. (Box 31)
- Kohls, Donald W.
  - Cedar Valley, 1959-1960.; 5 volumes (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
  - Prescott Quadrangle Minnesota-Wisconsin, 1957-1958.; 4 volumes (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
- Knapp, G. N.: Southern Minnesota., 2 volumes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Notes on sand complied in Southern Minnesota that were used as data for MGS Bulletin 18, 1918-1919.
- Leith, Charles K.: Vermilion District, 1908. (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Lobdell, H.
  - German Universities, 1898. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Canadian Border and Pine County, 1899. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Levoresen, Arville I. and Thomas M. Broderick: South Range, 1916.; 4 volumes (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Lovering, Thomas S.: North St. Louis County, 1921.; 4 volumes (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
- Lund, Ernest H.
  - Book 1 and 2, 1947.; 2 volumes (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Untitled, 1948. (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Marmaduke, Richard C.
  - Grand Marais, 1940. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Cook County, 1940.; 2 volumes (Box 20, Folder 7)
- McManus, Jeff: Lake Vermilion, 1969. (Box 23, Folder 11)
- Meeds, Alonzo Draper
  - Topographical and barometrical records, Northern Minnesota, 1893.; 3 volumes (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    Full and abstracted field notes for Northern Minnesota.
  - Rock samples, 1888. (Box 31)
- Morey, G.B.
  - Fond du Lac - Senior Thesis, 1956. (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Fond du Lac, undated. (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Gunflint, 1962. (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Rove I South Lake, Rove I-IV, 1962.; 4 volumes (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Soudan quad, 1965.; 3 volumes (Box 28, Folder 3-4)
  - Eagles Nest quad, 1965. (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Rove I Recon, undated. (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Rove II Recon, weather, undated. (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Rove III Recon, 1963. (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Rove IV Recon, Canada, undated. (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Rove VI Recon, Clearwater, undated. (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Mesabi deep drilling project, 1966-1967. (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Hibbing Sheet, 1966-1967.; 2 volumes (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Duluth Sheet, 1970. (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Stillwater, 1971. (Box 28, Folder 9)
- Mudrey, Michael G., Jr.
  - Air photos of Pigeon Point area, 1970-1972. (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Pigeon Point, 1970-1972.; 4 volumes (Box 26, Folder 5-7)
  - Cook County, 1971-1974. (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Shagawa Lake, 1973-1974. (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Nathan, Harold D.
  - South Lake quadrangle, 1966.; 3 volumes (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
  - Cook County - Duluth complex, Gunflint Lake, 1967-1968.; 3 volumes (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
- Ogaard, L. A.: Figures on leveling, 1893, 1897.; 3 volumes (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
- Olsen, B.: Magnetometer traverses, Tower-Soudan area, 1978.; 2 volumes (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Parham, Walter E.: Book 1 and 2, 1963.; 2 volumes (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Payne, C. Marshall: Gravity survey, New Brighton quad, 1964.; 2 volumes (Box 24, Folder 8)
  Also lists Norman Adamson and John Stone as geologists.
- Peckham, Stephen Farnham: Minnesota rocks and minerals, 1877-1897. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Pettijohn, Francis J.: St. Louis County, 1921. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Prokopovich, Nikola: Marl, 1956.; 2 volumes (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Riley, Charles A.: Bloating clays, 1948. (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Roepke, Harlan H.: Marl, 1956.; 2 volumes (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Sandberg, Adolph E.
  - Study of lava flows in Duluth Area, 1933-1936. (Box 31)
  - Location of samples-accessory minerals, 1935. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Sanders, C.W., Jr.: Snowbank Lake, circa 1922.; 2 volumes (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Schwartz, George M.
  - Cook County, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Gneiss Problem, South of Ely, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Ely Greenstone, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Keweenawan of Cook and Lake Counties, 1923. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Magnetics of Keweenawan, 1923.; 2 volumes (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Guidebook for Highway No. 1, 1924. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Rove Slate Area, 1925-1927.; 4 volumes (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Red Rock areas, 1929. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Gravel Deposits, 1921. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Anorthosites, 1929, 1931-1934, 1936.; 6 volumes (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
  - Duluth area, 1938-1940, 1942.; 3 volumes (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - Magnetometer notes, 1942.; 3 volumes (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - Magnetometer readings, Cloquet to Mesabi, 1940. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Magnetometer Gabbro contact traverses, 1942. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Duluth area, 1937-1941.; 4 volumes (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
  - Magnetometer notes, 1942. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Carlton area, Thomson formation, Atkinson to Denham, 1939-1940.; 2 volumes (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Twin City area, 1932-1933. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Lake and Cook County flows, 1952. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Soudan Mine, 1952. (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Sardeson, Frederick W.
  - Notebook, 1898. (Box 31)
  - Description of places visited with lists of fossils found, 1890. (Box 31)
- Seales, John N.
  - Traverse notes on Crane Lake, 1919. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Crane Lake (Compassmans' notes only), 1919. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Sims, Paul K.
  - Crab Lake and Ely NW quads; Itasca and Koochiching counties, 1966-1967. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Shagawa Lake and Crab Lake quads, 1967-1968. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Shagawa Lake quad, 1968. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Shagawa Lake, Lost Lake, Crab Lake and Soudan quads, 1969-1970. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Tower, Shagawa Lake, Crab Lake and Soudan quads, 1969-1971. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Angleworm Lake, Shagawa Lake quad, Minnesota River Valley and Central Minnesota, 1971-1974. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Crab Lake and Shagawa Lake quads, 1973. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Shagawa Lake and Chad Lake quads, 1973-1974. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Crab, Chad and Shagawa Lake quads, 1974-1975. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Chad Lake, Crab Lake and Soudan quads, 1975-1976. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Soudan, Eagles Nest and Crab Lake quads, 1976-1977. (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Soudan and Eagles Nest quads, 1977. (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Skillman, Margaret: Minnesota Valley and Central Minnesota, 1946. (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Sloan, Robert E.
  - Southeastern Minnesota, 1960. (Box 30)
  - Rochester mapping notes, 1959-1960. (Box 30)
  - Geologic mapping, Rochester area, 1958. (Box 30)
  - Southeastern Minnesota, Mankato and vicinity, 1954-1956. (Box 30)
  - GSA field trip notes, 1955. (Box 30)
- Soper, Edgar Kirke: Peat report and plant survey of pressed plants, 1915; 4 volumes (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  See also Percy G. Cowin.
- Southwick, David L.
  - Eagles Nest, Soudan I-III, 1977-1980.; 3 volumes (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
  - Vermilion District, 1980-1982. (Box 25, Folder 9)
- Spurr, Josiah Edward: Iron Range, 1893; 2 volumes (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Stauffer, Clinton R.
  - Stratigraphy, 1934. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Book No. 2-5, 1922-1924.; 4 volumes (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Book No. 6, Well records, 1924-1925. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Book No. 7, Faunal Lists, 1924. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Book No. 8-10, 1925-1928.; 3 volumes (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Book No. 11-16, 1923-1926, 1928-1931.; 6 volumes (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
  - Book No. 17-18, 1931-1932.; 2 volumes (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Stratigraphy, No. 19, 1934. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Book No. 27-34, 1938-1943.; 8 volumes (Box 18, Folder 3-7)
- St. Clair, George W.: Gillis Lake and Ogishkemunice Lake quads, undated. (Box 23, Folder 10)
- Sundeen, Stanley W.
  - Heavy residue work, Giants Ridge, 1934. (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Structure, Giants Ridge, 1935. (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Idaho Springs, Colorado, 1933. (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Taylor, Donald A.: T 63 N, R 4 W, 1938.; 2 volumes (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Thiel, George A.
  - Vermilion, 1920. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Vermilion, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Vermilion and Turtle, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Turtle Lake, 1920. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - North St. Louis County, 1921.; 4 volumes (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Cuyuna, 1921. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - North St. Louis County, 1922.; 2 volumes (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Volume 2 includes field maps.
  - Carleton County Cuyuna, 1922. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Cuyuna, 1923.; 2 volumes (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Cuyuna Drilling Madison collection, 1924. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Cuyuna, 1924. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Marl, 1927.; 4 volumes (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Minnesota River Valley, 1930.; 2 volumes (Box 14, Folder 6)